[Music]
welcome I'm very excited today to talk
about effective speaking in spontaneous
situations I thank you all for joining
us even though the title of my talk is
grammatically incorrect I thought that
might scare a few of you away but I
learned teaching here at the business
school catching people's attention is
hard so something as simple as that I
thought might draw a few of you here so
this is going to be a highly interactive
and participative
Workshop today if you don't feel
comfortable participating that's
completely fine but do know I'm going to
ask you to talk to people next to you
there'll be opportunities to stand up
and practice some things because I
believe the way we become effective
communicators is by actually
communicating so let's get started right
away I'd like to ask you all to read
this sentence and as you read this
sentence what's most important to me is
that you count the number of FS that you
find in this sentence please count the
number of FS keep it quiet to
yourself give you just another couple
seconds
here 3 two one raise your hand please if
you found three and only three FS
excellent great did anybody find four
okay anybody find only five fs and
anybody find six there's six FS
what two-letter word ending in f did
many of us miss
of we'll make sure to get this to you so
you can torment your friends and family
at a later
date when I first was exposed to this
over 12 years ago I only found three and
I felt really stupid so I like to start
every Workshop every class I teach with
this to pass that feeling and no no
that's not that's not why I do this I do
this because this is a perfect analogy
for what we're going to be talking about
today the vast majority of us in this
room very smart people in this room were
not as effective as we could have been
in this activity we didn't get it right
and the same is true when it comes to
speaking in public particularly when
spontaneous speaking it's little things
that make a big difference in being
effective So today we're going to talk
about little things in terms of your
approach your attitude your practice
that can change how you feel when you
speak in
public and we're going to be talking
primarily about one typee of public
speaking not the type that you plan for
in advance the type that you actually
spend time thinking about you might even
create slides for these are the Keynotes
the conference presentation the formal
toasts that's not what we're talking
about today we're talking about
spontaneous speaking when you're in a
situation that you're asked to speak off
the cuff and in the moment what we're
going through today is is actually the
result of a workshop I created here for
the business school several years ago a
survey was taken among the students and
they said what's one of the what are
things we could do to help make you more
successful here and at the top of that
list was this notion of responding to
cold calls does everybody know what a
cold call is it's where the mean
Professor like me looks at some students
says what do you think and there was a
lot of panic and a lot of Silence so as
a result of that this Workshop was
created in a vast majority of first year
students here at the GSB go through this
Workshop so I'm going to walk you
through sort of a hybrid version of what
they do the reality is that spontaneous
speaking is actually more prevalent than
plann speaking perhaps it's giving
introductions you're at a dinner and
somebody says you know so and so would
you mind introducing them maybe it's
giving feedback in the moment your boss
turns to you and says would you tell me
what you think it could be a surprise
toast or finally it could be during the
Q&A session and by the way we will leave
plenty of time at the end of our day
today for Q&A I'd love to hear the
questions you have about this topic or
other topics related to
communicating so our agenda is simple in
order to Be an Effective Communicator
regardless of if it's planned or
spontaneous you need to have your
anxiety under control so we'll start
there second what we're going to talk
about is some ground rules for the
interactivity we'll have today and then
finally we're going to get into the
heart of what we will be covering and
again as I said lots of activity and I
invite you to
participate so let's get started with
anxiety
management 85% of people tell us that
they're nervous when speaking in public
and I think the other 15% are lying okay
we could create a situation where we
could make them nervous too in fact just
this past week a study from Chapman
University asked Americans what are the
things you fear most and among being
caught in a surprise terrorist attack
having identity your identity stolen was
public speaking among the top five was
speaking in front of others this is a
ubiquitous fear and one that I believe
we can learn to manage and I use that
word manage very carefully because I
don't think we ever want to overcome it
anxiety actually helps us it gives us
energy helps us Focus tells us what
we're doing is important but we want to
learn to manage it so I'd like to
introduce you to a few techniques that
can work and all of these techniques are
based on academic research but before we
get there I'd love to ask you what does
it feel like when you're sitting in the
audience watching a nervous speaker
present how do you feel just shout out a
few things how do you
feel
uncomfortable I heard many of you going
yes uncomfortable it feels very awkward
doesn't it so what do we do now a couple
of you probably like watching somebody
suffer okay but most of us don't so what
do we do we sit there and we nod and we
smile or we
disengage and to the nervous speaker
looking out at his or her audience
seeing a bunch of people nodding or
disengaged that does not help okay so we
need to learn to manage our anxiety
because fundamentally your job as a
communicator rather regardless of if
it's planned or spontaneous is to make
your audience comfortable because if
they're comfortable they can receive
your message and when I say comfortable
I am not referring to the fact that that
your message has to be sugarcoated and
nice and them to hear it can be a harsh
message but they have to be in a place
where they can receive it so it's
incumbent on you as a communicator to
help your audience feel comfortable and
we do that by managing our anxiety so
let me introduce you to a few techniques
that I think you can use right away to
help you feel more
comfortable the first has to do with
when you begin to feel those anxiety
symptoms for most people this happens in
the initial minutes prior to
speaking in this situation what happens
is many of us begin to feel whatever it
is that happens to you maybe your
stomach gets a little gurgly maybe your
legs begin to shake maybe you begin to
perspire and then we start to say to
ourselves oh my goodness I'm nervous
uhoh they're going to tell I'm nervous
this is not going to go well and we
start spiraling out of
control so research on mindful attention
tells us that if when we begin to feel
those anxiety symptoms we simply greet
our anxiety and say hey this this is me
feeling nervous I'm about to do
something of
consequence and simply by greeting your
anxiety and acknowledging it that it's
normal and natural heck 85% of people
tell us they have it you actually can
stem the tide of that anxiety spiraling
out of control it's not necessarily
going to reduce the anxiety but it will
stop it from spinning up so the next
time you begin to feel those anx anxiety
signs take a deep breath and say this is
me feeling anxious
I notice a few of you taking some notes
there's a handout that will come at the
end that has everything that I'm
supposed to say okay can't guarantee I'm
going to say it but I you'll have it
there in addition to this approach a
technique that works very well and this
is a a technique that I helped do some
research on way back when I was in
graduate school has to do with reframing
how you see the speaking situation most
of us when we are up presenting planned
or spontaneous we feel that we have to
do it right and we feel like we are
performing how many of you have ever
acted done singing or dancing I'm not
going to ask for performances now okay
many of you have we should note that we
could do next year maybe a talent show
of alums it looks like we got the talent
there that's
great so when you perform you know that
there's a right way and a wrong way to
do it if you don't hit your the right
note or your right line at the right
time at the right place you've made a
mistake it messes up the audience it
messes up the people on stage but when
you present there is no right way
there's certainly better and worse ways
but there is no one right way so we need
to look at presenting as something other
than performance and what I'd like to
suggest is what we need to see this as
is a
conversation right now I'm having a
conversation with a 100 plus
people rather than saying I'm performing
for you but it's not enough just to say
this is a conversation I want to give
you some concrete things you can do
first start with questions questions by
their very nature are dialogic they're
two-way what was one of the very first
things I did here for you I had you
count the number of fs and raise your
hands I asked you a question that gets
your audience involved it makes it feel
to me as the presenter as if we are in
conversation so use questions they can
be rhetorical they can be polling
perhaps I actually want to hear
information from you
in fact I use questions when I create an
outline for my presentations rather than
writing bullet points I list questions
that I'm going to answer and that puts
me in that conversational mode if you
were to look at my notes for today's
talk you'll see it's just a series of
questions right now I'm answering the
question how do we manage our
anxiety Beyond questions another very
useful technique for making us
conversational is to use conversational
language
many nervous speakers distance
themselves physically if you've ever
seen a nervous speaker present he or she
will say something like this welcome I
am really excited to be here with
you they pull as far away from you as
possible because you threaten us
speakers you make us nervous so we want
to get away from you we do the same
thing linguistically we use language
that distances ourselves It's Not
Unusual to hear a nervous speaker say
something like one must consider the
ramifications
or today we're going to cover step one
step two step three that's very
distancing language to be more
conversational use conversational
language instead of one must consider
say this is important to you we all need
to be concerned with do you hear that
inclusive conversational language has to
do with the pronouns instead of step one
step two step three first what we need
to do is this the second thing you
should consider is
here use conversational language so
being conversation can also help you
manage your
anxiety the third technique I'd like to
share is research that I actually
started when I was an undergraduate here
I was very fortunate to study with Phil
zimbardo of the Stanford Prison
Experiment Fame many people don't know
that Zim actually was instrumental in
starting one of the very first shinness
institutes in the world and especially
in the country and I did some research
with him that looked at how your
orientation to time influences is how
you react and what we learned is if you
can bring yourself into the present
moment rather than being worried about
the future
consequences you can actually be less
nervous most of us when we present are
worried about the future consequences my
students are worried they're not going
to get the right grade some of you are
worried you might not get the funding
you might not get the support you might
not get the laughs that you want all of
those are future States so if we can
bring ourselves into the present moment
we're not going to be is concerned about
those future States and therefore will
be less nervous there are lots of ways
to become present
oriented I know a professional speaker
he's paid
$10,000 an hour to speak it's a good gig
he gets very nervous he's up in front of
crowds of thousands behind the stage
what he does is a hundred push-ups right
before he comes out you can't be that
physically active and not be in the
present moment now I'm not recommending
all of us go to that level of exertion
cuz he starts out of breath sweaty right
but a walk around the building before
you speak that can do it there are other
ways if you've ever watched athletes
perform and get ready to do their event
they listen to music they focus on a
song or a playlist that helps get them
in the moment you can do things as
simple as counting backwards from a
hundred by tough numbers like
17 I'm going to pause because I know
people in the room are trying yeah gets
hard after that third or fourth one I
know my favorite way to get present
oriented is is to say tongue
twisters saying a tongue twister forces
you to be in the moment otherwise you'll
say it wrong and it has the added
benefit of warming up your voice most
nervous speakers don't warm up their
voice they Retreat inside themselves and
start saying all these bad things to
themselves so saying a tongue twister
can help you be both present oriented
and warm up your
voice remember I said today we're going
to have a lot of participation I'm going
to ask you to repeat after me my
favorite tongue twister and I like this
tongue twister because if you say get
wrong you say a naughty word and I'm
going to be listening to see if I hear
any naughty words this
morning repeat after me it's only three
phrases I slit a
sheet a sheet I
slit and on that slitted sheet I
sit oh very good no shits
excellent very good now in that moment
in that moment
you weren't worried about I'm in front
of all these people this is weird this
guy's having me do this you were so
focused on saying it right and trying to
figure out what the naughty word was
that you were in the present moment
that's how easy it is so it's very
possible for us to manage our anxiety we
can do it initially by greeting the
anxiety when we begin to feel those
signs we can do it when we reframe the
situation as a
conversation and we do it when we become
present oriented those are three of many
tools that exist to help you manage your
anxiety if you have questions about
other ways I'm happy to chat with you
and at the end I'm going to point you to
some resources that you can refer to to
help you find additional sources for
you so let's get started on the core
part of what we're doing today which is
how to feel more comfortable speaking in
spontaneous situations some very simple
ground rules for
you first
I'm going to identify four steps that I
believe are critical to becoming
effective at speaking in in a
spontaneous situation with each of those
steps I'm going to ask you to
participate in an activity none of them
are more painful than saying the tongue
twister out loud they may require you to
stand up they might require you to talk
to the person next to you but none of
them are painful and then finally I'm
going to conclude with a phrase or
saying that comes from the wonderful
world of
improvisation through the continuing
studies program here at Stanford for the
past 5 years I have co-taught a class
with Adam Tobin he is a lecturer in the
uh creative arts department he teaches
film and New Media and he's an expert at
improv and we've partnered together to
help people learn how to speak more
spontaneously we call it
improvisationally speaking and Adam has
taught me wonderful phrases and ideas
from improv that I want to impart to you
they really stick that's why I'm sharing
them with you to help you remember these
techniques and again at the end of all
this you'll get a handout that has this
listed so let's get started the very
first thing that gets in people's way
when it comes to spontaneous speaking is
themselves we get in our own way we want
to be perfect we want to give the right
answer we want our toast to be
incredibly memorable these things are
burdened by our effort by our trying the
best thing we can do the first step in
our process is to get ourselves out of
the way easier said than done most of us
in this room are in this room because we
are type A personalities we work hard we
think fast we make sure that we get
things right but that can actually serve
as a disservice as we try to speak in
the
moment I'd like to demonstrate a little
of this for you and I need your help to
do that so we're going to do our first
activity we are going to do an activity
that's called Shout the wrong name in a
moment if you are able and willing I'm
going to ask you to stand and I am going
to ask you for about 30 seconds to look
all around you in this environment and
you are going to point at different
things and I know it's rude to point but
for this exercise please point I want
you to point to things and you are going
to call the things you are pointing to
out loud anything but what they really
are so I might point to this and say
refrigerator I might point to this and
say cat I am pointing to anything in
your environment around you can be the
person sitting next to you standing next
to you you will just shout and shouting
is important the wrong
name so in a moment I'm going to ask you
to stand and do that please raise your
hand if you already have the first five
or six things you're going to call
out yeah that's what I'm talking about
we stockpile you all are excellent game
players I told you the game shout the
wrong name and you have already begun
figuring out how you're going to master
the game that's your brain trying to
help you get it
right I'd like to suggest the only way
you can get this activity wrong is by
doing what you've just
done there is no way to get this wrong
okay even if I call this a chair no
penalty will be bestowed upon you
okay CU I won't know what you were
pointing at you could have been pointing
at the floor under the chair and you
called the floor the chair and you were
fine the point is we are planning and
working to get it right and there is no
way to get it right just doing it gets
it right okay so let's try this now
we're going to play this game twice
again it's for 30 seconds if you are
willing and able will you please stand
up you can do this seated by the way but
if you're willing and able let's stand
up okay in a moment I am about to say go
and I would like for you to point at
anything around here including me it's
okay to point at me I hope it's not a
bad thing you say when you point at me
but point at different things and loudly
and proudly call them different than
what they are ready
begin
porcupine
California salt
shaker
car
Library tennis
racket per
purple
orange
putrid
hello
time
time let's you can stay standing because
in a mere moments we're going to do it
again so if you're comfortable standing
we're about to do it again first thank
you that was wonderful I heard great
words being called out it was it was fun
and some of you in the back were doing
it in sync so it looked like you were
doing 7s disco dance it was awesome okay
this this was great now let me ask you
just a few questions did you notice
anything about the words that you were
saying did we find patterns perhaps
maybe some of you were going through
fruits and vegetables a few of you were
going through things that started with
the letter
a right that's your brain saying okay
you told me not to stockpile so I'm
going to try to be a little more devious
and I'm going to give you p
patterns okay same
problem when we teach that class I told
you about that improvisationally
speaking class we like to say your brain
is there to help you these things it's
doing have helped you be successful but
like a windshield wiper we just want to
wipe those suggestions away and see what
happens okay so we're going to do this
activity
again this time try the best you can to
thank your brain if it provides you with
patterns or stock piles and just say
thank you brain
and disregard them okay so let's see
what happens when we're not stockpiling
and we're not playing off patterns we'll
do this for only 15 seconds see how this
feels baby steps ready
begin
Kodak bicycle chain
skateboard
bananas
purple putrid
time please have a seat thank you
again did you notice a
difference between the second time and
the first time yes was it a little
easier that second time
no that's okay we're just starting these
skills are not like a light switch it's
not like you learn these SKS skills and
then all of the sudden you can execute
on them this is a wonderful game this is
a wonderful game to train your brain to
get out of its own way you can play this
game anywhere anytime I like to play
this game when I'm sitting in
traffic makes me feel better than the I
shout things out they're not the naughty
things that I want to be shouting out
but I shout out things and it helps
you're training yourself to get out of
your own way you're working against the
muscle memory that you've developed over
the course of your life with a brain
that acts very fast to help you solve
problems but in essence in spontaneous
speaking situations you put too much
pressure on yourself trying to figure
out how to get it
right so a game like this teaches us to
get out of our own way it teaches us to
see the things that we do that prevent
us from acting
spontaneously in essence we are reacting
rather than responding to react means to
act again you've thought it and now
you're acting on it that takes too long
and it's too thoughtful we want to
respond in a way that's genuine and
authentic so the maxim I would like for
you to take from this and again these
maxims come from improvisation is one of
my favorite dare to be dull and in a
room like this telling you dare to be
dull is offensive and I apologize but
this will help rather than stre striving
for
greatness dare to be dull and if you
dare to be D D and allow yourself that
you will reach that greatness it's when
you set greatness as your target that it
gets in the way of you ever getting
there because you over evaluate you
overanalyze you freeze up so the first
step in our process today is to get out
of Our Own Way dare to be dull easier
said than done but once you practice in
a game just as simple as the one we
practiced is a great way to do
it but that's not enough getting out of
our own way is important but the second
step of our process has us change how we
see the situation we find ourselves in
we need to see the speaking opportunity
that we are a part of as an opportunity
rather than a challenge and a
threat when I coach Executives on Q&A
skills when they go in front of the
media or whatever
investors they see it as an adversarial
experience
me versus them and one of the first
things I work on is change the way you
approach it a Q&A session for example is
an opportunity for you it's an
opportunity to clarify it's an
opportunity to understand what people
are thinking so if we look at it as an
opportunity it feels very different we
see it differently and therefore we have
more freedom to respond when I feel that
you are challenging me I am going to do
the bare minimum to respond and protect
myself
if I see this as an opportunity where I
have a chance to explain and expand I'm
going to interact differently with you
so spontaneous speaking situations are
ones that afford you
opportunities so when you're at a
corporate dinner and your boss turns to
you and says oh you know him better than
the rest would you mind introducing him
you say great thank you for the
opportunity rather
than right I better get this
right so see things as an opportunity
commity I have a game to play to help us
with this this is a fun one the holidays
are approaching we all in this room are
going to give and receive gifts here's
how this game will work it works best if
you have a partner so I'm hoping you can
work with somebody sitting next to you
if there's nobody sitting next to you
turn around introduce yourself great way
to connect if not you can play this game
by yourself it's just a little harder
and you can't do the second part of the
game so after I explain the game this
gives you a chance to to get to know
somebody here's how it works if you have
a partner you and your partner are going
to exchange imaginary gifts okay pretend
you have a gift can be a big gift can be
a small gift and you will give your gift
to your
partner your partner will take the gift
and open it up and will tell you what
you gave them because you have no you
just gave them a gift so you are going
to open up the box and you're going to
look inside and you are going to say the
first thing that comes to your mind in
the moment not the thing you have all
just thought
of or the thing after that remember what
we talked about before that still plays
that's still in play okay you're
stockpiling look in there my favorite
that I said somebody gave me this a gift
during playing this game I looked inside
and I saw a frog leg I don't know why I
saw a frog leg but that's what I said
that's the first part of the activity
now the opportunity is twofold in this
game the opportunity is for you the gift
receiver to name a gift that's kind of
fun that's an opportunity it's not a
threat but the real opportunity is for
the Gift Giver because the Gift Giver
then has to
say so you look in you say thank you for
giving me a frog's leg and the person
will will look at you and say I knew you
wanted a frog's leg because so whatever
you find the person who has received it
is going to say absolutely I'm so glad
you're happy I got it for you because so
you have to respond to whatever they say
right what a great opportunity now some
of you are sitting there going oh that's
hard I don't want to do I'm going to
make a fool out of myself others of you
are if you're following this advice are
saying what a great opportunity right so
the game again is played like this you
and your partner will exchange a each
will exchange a gift one will start then
the other will follow the first person
will give a gift to the second person
second person opens the Box however big
the box is and if the box is big and you
find a penny in it perfect doesn't
matter if the box is heavy and you find
a feather in it fine it does there's no
way to get it wrong wrong okay
whatever's in the box is in the Box you
can return it and get what you wanted
later
okay the person then you will name it
you will say thank you for the whatever
you saw in the Box the person who gave
it to you will say I'm so glad you're
excited I got it for you
because and you will give a reason that
you got them whatever they decided you
gave them make sense all right so very
quickly just in 5 seconds find a partner
if you're willing to do this with a
partner everybody have a partner
okay all right in your
Partnerships in your
Partnerships pick an a person and a b
person you may stand or sit it's totally
up to
you pick an A and pick a
b okay B goes
first all
right B give a a gift B give a a gift a
thank them and then B will name and give
the reason they gave it to him
[Applause]
if you have not switched switch please
let's wrap it up in 30 seconds please
let's wrap it
up all right if we can all have our
seats
if we can
all take our seats
please I know I'm telling a room of
many MBA alums to stop talking and
that's
hard all right ladies and
gentlemen did you get what you
wanted pretty neat huh you always get
what you want
now for some of you this was really hard
because you you were really taking the
challenge and not seeing what was in the
Box until you looked in there okay was
anybody surprised by what you found in
the Box what did you find sir what was
in the
Box
what uh
wow nice nice if you've got a Ferrari
you need a transmission I like it who
else found something that was surprising
what did you find a live unicorn a live
unicorn that's a great gift right how
was it as the Gift Giver were you
surprised at what your partner found in
the Box isn't it interesting that when
we give an imaginary gift knowing that
the person's going to name it we already
have in mind what they're going to find
and when they say live unicorn we go
well that's interesting right
so the point of this game is to one
remind ourselves we have to get out of
our own way like we talked about before
but to see this as an opportunity and to
have fun I love watching people play
this game the number of smiles that I
saw amongst you and and I have to admit
when I first started some of you looked
a little dower a little doubting okay
but in that last game you were all
smiling and looked like you were having
fun so when you reframe the spontaneous
speaking opportunity as as an
opportunity as something that you can
co-create and share all of the sudden
you are less nervous less defensive and
you can accomplish something pretty darn
good in this case a fun
outcome this reminds us of perhaps the
most famous of all improvisation sayings
yes and a lot of us live our
communication lives saying no
but yes and opens up a tremendous amount
of opportunities and this doesn't mean
you have to say yes and to a question
somebody asked this just means the
approach you take to the
situation so you're going to ask me
questions that's an opportunity yes and
will follow through versus no in being
defensive so we've accomplished the
first two steps of our process first we
get out of our own way and second we
reframe the situation as an
opportunity the next phase is also hard
but very rewarding and that is to slow
down and listen you need to understand
the demands of the requirement you find
yourself in in order to respond
appropriately
but often we jump ahead we listen just
enough to think we got it and then we go
ahead starting our to think about what
we're going to respond and then we
respond we really need to listen because
fundamentally as a communicator your job
is to be in service of your audience and
if you don't understand what your
audience is asking or needs you can't
fulfill that obligation so we need to
slow down and
listen I have a fun game to play
in this game you are going to s p l l e
v r y t h i n g y o u s a y t o y o u r
p a r t n e
r i will
translate you're going to get with the
same partner you just worked with and
you are going to have a very brief
conversation about something fun that
you plan to do today I know this is the
most fun you're going to have all day
but the next fun thing you're going to
do today you are going to tell your
partner what you are going to do that
will be fun today but you are going to
do so by s p l l i n g it
t okay so you're going to spell
it it's okay if you are not a good
speller okay the I you'll see the
benefit of doing this so with the
partner you just worked with person a is
going to go first this time you are
simply going to tell your partner
actually you're going to expell to your
partner what it is of fun something of
fun that you're going to do today okay
do what you were really going to do for
fun and not do things like Fe d t h e c
a t right just because you don't want to
spell right so you can use big words all
right 30 seconds each spell to your
partner something fun that you're going
to do
today would you like to play
go g o t h e g a m
e oh my goodness say it again spell it
again o y t h yep g a m e ex c e l l n t
i h o p e t h a t t h e y w i
n c l n thank you that was very good
thank you
if you have not switched switch take 30
more seconds with the new partner
spelling
g a t exclamation point t a n k y o u p
l e a s e t a k e y o u r s e a t
so what did we
learn what did we learn besides that
we're not so good at spelling got to
pause between the words you have to
pause between the
words how did this change your
interaction with the person you were
interacting with what did you have to do
Focus FOC focus and
listen and you can't be thinking ahead
you have to be in the moment when you
listen and truly understand what the
person is trying to say then you can
respond in a better way a more targeted
response we often don't
listen so we start by getting out of our
own way we then reframe the situation as
an opportunity those are things we do
inside our head but in the moment of
interacting we have to listen first
before we can respond to the spontaneous
request perhaps my most favorite
Maxim comes from this activity don't
just do something stand
there
listen listen and then
respond now how do we respond that
brings us to the fourth part of our
process and that is we have to tell a
story we respond in a way that has a
structure all stories have structure we
have to respond in a structured way the
the key to successful spontaneous
speaking and by the way planed speaking
is having a
structure I would like to introduce you
to two of the most prevalent and popular
and useful structures you can use to
communicate a message in a spontaneous
situation but before we get there we
have to talk about the value of
structure it increases what is called
processing fluency the effectiveness of
which or through which we process
information we actually process
structured information roughly 40% more
effectively and efficiently than
information that's not structured I love
looking out in this audience because you
will remember as I remember phone
numbers when you had to remember them if
you wanted to call somebody okay Young
Folks today don't need to remember phone
numbers they just need to look at a
picture push a button and then the voice
starts talking on the other end 10-digit
phone numbers it's actually hard to
remember 10-digit phone numbers how did
you do it you chunked it into a
structure three three and four structure
helps us
remember the same is true when speaking
spontaneously or in a planned situation
so let me introduce you to two useful
structures the first useful structure
you have probably heard or used in some
Incarnation it is the problem solution
benefit structure you start by talking
about what the issue is the
problem you then talk about a way of
solving it and then you talk about the
benefits of following through on it very
persuasive very effective helps you as
the speaker remember it helps your
audience know where where you're going
with it when I was a tour guide on this
campus many many many years
ago what do you think the single most
important thing they drilled into our
head it took a full quarter by the way
to train to be a tour guide here they
used to line us up at one end of the
quad and have us walk backwards straight
and if you failed you had to start over
to this day I can walk backwards in a
straight line because of that as part of
that training what do you think the most
important thing they taught us
was never lose your tour
group I'm not Jo never that's never lose
your tour
group the same is true as a presenter
never lose your audience the way you
keep your audience on track is by
providing structure none of you would go
on a tour with me if I said hi my name
is Matt let's
go you want to know where you're going
why you're going there how long it's
going to take you need to set
expectations and structure does that
problem solution benefit is a wonderful
structure to have in your back
pocket it's something that you can use
quickly when you're in the
moment it can be reframed so it's not
always a problem you're talking about
maybe it's an opportunity maybe there's
a market opportunity you want to go out
and capture it's not a problem that
we're not doing it but maybe we'd be
better off if we did so it becomes
opportunity solution which are the steps
to achieve it and then the
benefit another structure which works
equally equally well is the what so what
now what structure you start by talking
about what it is then you talk about why
it's important and then what the next
steps
are this is a wonderful formula for
answering questions for introducing
people so if in the moment somebody ask
me to introduce somebody I change the
what to who I say who they are why
they're important and what we're going
to do next maybe listen to them maybe
drink our wine whatever right what so
what now what the reality is this when
you are in a spontaneous speaking
situation you have to do two things
simultaneously you have to figure out
what to say and how to say it these
structures help you by telling you how
to say
it if you can become comfortable with
these structures you can be in a
situation where you can respond very a
to spontaneous speaking
situations we're going to practice
because that's what we do here's the
situation is everybody familiar with
this child's toy it's a Slinky okay you
are going to sell this Slinky to your
partner using either problem solution
benefit or opportunity solution benefit
what does the slinky provide
you or you could use what so what now
what what is it why is it important and
the next steps might be to buy it okay
so by using that structure see how
already it helps you it helps you
focus get with your partner and we're
only going to have one part partner sell
to the other partner okay so get with
your partner one of you will volunteer
to sell to the other okay sell a slinky
using problem solution benefit or what
so what now what please begin
yeah so we have the handouts but I'm
also going to be doing the the
microphone so uh when I debrief this you
can go ahead and pass them out does that
make sense after after QA no no um after
this activity okay and after that we'll
do
correct e
30 more seconds
please excellent let's all close the
deal seal the deal
I have never
seen more people in one place doing this
at the same
time I love it I teach people to gesture
and gesture big it's great I love it so
if you were the recipient of the the
sales pitch thumbs up did they do a good
job did they use the structure awesome
I'm recruiting you all for my next
business as my
salese please try to ignore this but as
we're speaking the handout I told you
about is coming around on the back of
that handout you are going to see a list
of structures the two we talked about
and several others that can help you in
spontaneous speaking situations these
structures help because they help you
understand how you're going to say what
you say structure sets you free and I
know that's kind of ironic but it's true
if you have that structure then you're
free to think about what it is you're
going to say it reduces the cognitive
load of figuring out what you're saying
and how you're going to say it all of
this is on that handout
okay so what does this all mean it means
that we have within our
ability the tools and the approaches to
help us in spontaneous speaking
situations the very first thing we have
to do is manage our anxiety because you
can't be an effective speaker if you
don't have your anxiety under control
and we talked about how you can do that
by greeting your anxiety reframing as a
conversation and being in the present
moment once you do that you need to
practice a series of four steps that
will help you speak spontaneously first
you get out of your own way I would love
it if all of you on your way from here
to the football game point at things and
call them the wrong name it'll be fun if
most of us do it then it won't be weird
if only one and two of us do it it'll be
weird right second give gifts
by that I mean see your interactions as
ones of opportunity not
challenges third take the time to
listen
listen and then finally use structures
and you have to practice these
structures I practice these structures
on my kids I have two kids when they ask
me questions I usually answer them in
what so what now what they don't know it
but when they go over to their friends
houses and they see their friends ask
their dad's questions they don't get
what so so what now what so you know you
have to practice the more you practice
the more comfortable you will
become ultimately you have the
opportunity before you to become more
compelling more confident more connected
as a speaker if you leverage these
techniques if you're interested in
learning more this is where I do a
little plug okay I've written a book
many of the MBA students who take the
Strategic communication classes here
that I and others teach read it it's
called speaking up without freaking
out more importantly there's a website
here that I curate called no freaking
speaking and it has lots of information
that I've written and others have
written about how to become more
effective at speaking so that's that's
the end of my plug what I'd really like
to do is enter into a spontaneous
speaking situation with you and I would
love to entertain any questions that you
have there are two people who are
running around with microphones so some
of us who remember the Phil Donahue show
uh we're going to do a little bit of
that uh if you have a question the
microphone will come and I'm happy to
answer
it I think if it on yeah we can hear you
great um can you talk about hostile
situations hostile situations yes so
when you find yourself in a challenging
situation first it should not become a
surprise to you it should not be a
surprise before you ever speak you
should think about what is the
environment going to be like so it
shouldn't surprise you that there might
be some challenges in the
room when there are hostile situations
that arise you have have to acknowledge
it so if somebody says that's a
ridiculous idea why did you come up with
that to Simply say so the idea I came up
with was right acknowledge the emotion I
recommend not naming the
emotion okay so you sound really angry
person say I'm not angry I'm frustrated
now we're arguing over their mental
state right emotional state so so I say
something like I hear you have a lot of
passion on this issue or I hear there's
great concern from you so you
acknowledge the emotion because
otherwise it sits in the room and then
reframe a respond the way that makes
sense so if somebody raises their hand
and says your product is ridiculously
priced why do you charge so
much I might say I hear great concern
and what you're really asking about is
the value of our product and I would
give my value proposition and then I
would come back and say and because of
the value we provide we believe it's
priced fairly so you answer the question
about price but you reframe it in a way
that you feel more comfortable answering
it so the way to do this is to practice
all the skills we just talked about the
only skill that I'm adding to this is
the awareness in advance that you might
be in that situation first I have to
truly listen to what I'm hearing right
it's very easy for me when I hear a
challenging question to get all
defensive and not hear what the person's
asking I see it as an opportunity to
reframe and explain okay so again you
have to practice but that's how I think
you address it are there other questions
I see a question back here yes please
yes first of all thank you very much
great great presentation uh for a lot of
the the um the speaking I do I have
remote audiences audiences distributed
all over uh the country with uh Telecom
any tips for those kinds of audiences so
when you are speaking in a situation
where not everybody is collocated okay
in fact right at this very moment there
are people watching this presentation
remotely what you need to do is be
mindful of it second try to include
engagement techniques where the audience
actually has to do something so So
Physical participation is what we did
here through the games you can ask your
audience to imagine something imagine
what it would be like if when we try to
achieve a goal rather than saying here's
the goal we're trying to achieve say
imagine what it would be like if see
what that does to you it pulls you in I
can take polling questions most of the
technology that you're referring to has
some kind of polling feature you can
open up some kind of Wiki or Google doc
or some collaborative tool where people
can be doing things and you can be
monitoring that while you're presenting
so I might take some breaks I talk for
10 15 minutes and say okay let's apply
this and let's go into this Google doc
I've created and I see what people are
doing so it's about variety and it's
about engagement those are the ways that
you really connect to people who are
remote from you okay other
questions who you're pointing oh I've
got to look for where the mic is yes
please um this may be a similar to the
first question but um I do a lot of
expert witness testimony what's your
recommendation for handling
cross-examination specifically
specifically being cross-examined right
that's very hostile so in any speaking
situation that you go into that has some
planned element to it I recommend
identifying certain themes that you
think are important or believe need to
come out and then with each one of those
themes have some examples and concrete
evidence that you can use to support it
you don't go in with
memorized terms or ways of saying it you
just have ideas and themes and then you
put them together as necessary so when
I'm in a situation where people are
interrogating me uh I have certain
themes that I want to get across and
make sure that I I can do that in a way
that fits the needs in the moment if
it's hostile again you the the single
best tool you have to buy yourself time
and to help you answer a question
efficiently is paraphrasing the
paraphrase is like the Swiss army knife
of communication if you remember the
show mcgyver it's your mver tool right
so when a question comes in the way you
paraphrase it allows you the opportunity
to reframe it to think about your answer
and to pause and make sure you got it
right so when you're under those
situations if you have the opportunity
to paraphrase say so what you're really
asking about is X Y and Z that gives you
the opportunity to employ one of these
techniques now I've never been an expert
witness because I'm not an expert on
anything but those tools I believe could
be helpful the the microphone is back
there thank you thank you so much this
has been so helpful and enjoyable this
morning thank you would would you please
show the last screen so we can get down
the name of the book that you've written
and the information absolutely thank you
I think they actually there you might
even have an opportunity to it's on the
sheet too everything I said is on the
back of that sheet but I'm happy to have
this behind me while I while I talk
other questions yes please yes um I work
with um groups that from that represent
many different cultural backgrounds yes
so are there any caveats or is this a un
unversal
strategy so in terms of from your
perspective as the speaker I believe
this applies but when you whenever you
communicate part of the listening aspect
is also thinking about is who is my
audience and what are their expectations
so what are the cultural expectations of
the audience that I'm presenting to so
there might be certain norms and rules
that are expected so when I travel and
do talks I have to take into account
where I'm doing the the presentation so
I I'm I help present in the ignite
program and if you have not heard about
the ignite program here at the GSB it's
fantastic and I just did a presentation
standing in one of these awesome
classrooms that have all these cameras
and I just taught 35 people in Santiago
Chile right and I needed to understand
the cultural expectations of that area
and what they expect and what they're
willing to do when I ask them to
participate so it it's a part of that
listening step where you reflect on what
are the expectations of the audience I
think we have for two more questions and
then I'm going to hang afterwards if
anybody has individual questions but
some of these folks really want me to
keep on schedule yes please I wanted to
ask a question one of the things that
you've done effectively in your talking
and I've seen other effective speakers
do is interject humor in their talk how
what are the risks and rewards of trying
to do that well first thank you and I
appreciate all of you laughing those are
that's the sum total of all my jokes
you've heard them I am not funny Beyond
those jokes so humor is wonderfully
connecting it's wonderfully connecting
it's a great tool for connection it is
very very risky cultural reasons get in
the way sometimes what you think is
funny isn't funny to other people what
research tells us is that if you're
going to try to be funny
self-deprecating humor is your best bet
okay because it is the least risky there
is nothing worse than putting out a joke
and having no response it actually sets
you back farther than if you would have
gotten where you would have gotten if
the joke would have hit
so basic fundamentals you need to think
about with humor one is it funny how do
I know I ask other people first second
what happens if it doesn't work have a
backup plan right and then third if
you're worried about the answers to
those first two don't do it right one
last question please the microphone is
right here and then like I said I will
hang around afterwards yes please I um
I'm sort of on the opposite side of this
since I am a journalist and I frequently
have to ask spontaneous questions of
people who have been through media
training yes
so so any tips for chinks in the armor
way to ask ask a question without being
antagonistic but get a fact simile of a
straight answer well so let me give you
two answers one is I I have young boys
and the power of the why is great just
ask why a couple times and and you can
get through that first two layers of
training you know why do you say that
well how do you feel about that uh the
the second bit is
to what I have found successful in
getting people to I do this to get
people to answer in a more authentic way
what I'll do is I'll ask them to give
advice so what advice would you give
somebody who's challenged with this or
what advice would you give to somebody
in this situation and by asking for the
advice it changes the relationship they
have to me as the question asker and I
often get much more Rich detailed
information so the power of the why and
then put them in a position of providing
guidance and that can really
work with that I am going to thank you
very much I welcome you to ask questions
later and enjoy the rest of your reunion
weekend thank you
[Applause]
[Music]